<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>任任的藍色虛空 - 桿秤人生</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/category/gan-cheng-ren-sheng/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.poren.tw/</id><updated>2017-01-15T02:56:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>The Stratosphere Phenomenon</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/2017/01/15/the-stratosphere-phenomenon-an-essay/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-15T02:56:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-01-15T02:56:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Poren Chiang</name></author><id>tag:blog.poren.tw,2017-01-15:/2017/01/15/the-stratosphere-phenomenon-an-essay/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Stratosphere Phenomenon&lt;/i&gt; was the semester report I turned in on Professor Charles Wharton’s &lt;i&gt;Media Law, New Technology, and Constitutional Rights&lt;/i&gt;. It was completed under the stress of final and long before I had proper understanding to the U.S. legal system; but I realized it would be lost eventually in the digital age, and publishing would at least enable some random strangers to get some use out of it. Please feel free to share your thoughts and criticism on this amateur work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;「同溫層現象」是我在 105-1 修 Professor Charles Wharton 的「媒體法、新技術與憲法權利」寫的期末報告。最近在整理研究所的申請資料時，意識到這些不成熟的寫作內容終將塵封在歲月痕跡之中；將它們放到網路上，反而比較容易發揮點價值吧；還請路過的朋友不吝指教了。 (2018/10)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Stratosphere Phenomenon&lt;/i&gt; was the semester report I turned in on Professor Charles Wharton’s &lt;i&gt;Media Law, New Technology, and Constitutional Rights&lt;/i&gt;. It was completed under the stress of final and long before I had proper understanding to the U.S. legal system; but I realized it would be lost eventually in the digital age, and publishing would at least enable some random strangers to get some use out of it. Please feel free to share your thoughts and criticism on this amateur work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;「同溫層現象」是我在 105-1 修 Professor Charles Wharton 的「媒體法、新技術與憲法權利」寫的期末報告。最近在整理研究所的申請資料時，意識到這些不成熟的寫作內容終將塵封在歲月痕跡之中；將它們放到網路上，反而比較容易發揮點價值吧；還請路過的朋友不吝指教了。 (2018/10)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="XKCD: Online Communities 2 by Randall Munroe, CC BY-NC 2.5" src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/online_communities_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internet has never been more dominant in real world lives. Mobile devices connect us with rest of the world on-the-fly, while cloud computing and real-time synchronization breaks the barrier between physical storage and data-centers with nearly infinite capacities. In lieu of newspapers, traditional agencies now compete directly with artists, independent journalists, YouTube broadcasters, friends and families and wherever those cat photos came from — all have their presence on social media. Information produced too fast for us to consume, thus the invention of various algorithms to show us the most relevant pictures and posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Stratosphere Phenomenon” (同溫層現象) is how Taiwan’s netizens describe content filtering: in same altitude with little airflow convection, we could only seek warmth from those with familiar temperature, effectively limiting our field of view; fake news reports spread virally across the Internet, out of the reach of their correct counterparts. In this essay, we’ll explore why and how problematic comments would be censored, status quo and related controversies, and how an  appealing model of Internet regulation could be imposed with freedom of speech in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Dark Side of Social Network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early days of Internet, Information got delivered in a decentralized manner. News propagated through mailing lists and news forums, while ancient “search engines” are nothing more than a category of available websites. Since the flow of information was relatively small, they were presented in their original form, sorted whether chronologically or alphabetically. Chaotic it seems, spam and abusive contents on the Internet were rare, while moderators could easily take down problematic content from server cache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Year has since passed, and Internet today has grown beyond the control power of a single unified community. The concept of personalized web (a.k.a. Web 2.0) influenced the creation of social media websites, which quickly iterated and become the dominant communication service throughout the Internet. As of September 2016, there are 1.18 billion daily active users on Facebook&lt;sup id="fnref-1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, while daily Twitter tweets have grown over 50 million in 2010&lt;sup id="fnref-2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In order to keep pace with ever-increasing amount of speeches, social media websites present users with information they concern most — what individuals could see on their Social Network Service (SNS) are determined by suggestion algorithms, which is opaque to the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harmless as it seems, feeding users with favorable contents has posed serious impacts when it comes to public issues. Heavily biased news tend to oust neutral ones on popularity, ranking them with higher importance and visibility. Social network nowadays face challenges of extreme content&lt;sup id="fnref-3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, propagators of hate have used the new medium as a powerful tool to reach new audiences, as well as to spread racist propaganda and incite violence offline.&lt;sup id="fnref-4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used to count on “marketplace of ideas&lt;sup id="fnref-5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;” to drive false information out, but finding contrary perspectives now requires much, much more effort. Comparing the potential damage of problematic speeches with possible restoration action performable by the court, we might came agree that &lt;em&gt;some kind of regulation need to be imposed&lt;/em&gt;, despite of its form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“Report Abuse” mechanism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current social media impose certain mechanism to bring down problematic comments, which is known as “report abuse.” Twitter, for example, accepts reports on pornography, impersonation, violent threats, spam, and other violations of Twitter Terms of Service&lt;sup id="fnref-6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Loosely-based on existing copyright infringement reporting mechanism (which dated back to 1996 &lt;em&gt;Digital Millennium Copyright Act&lt;/em&gt;), they allow social network users to file complaint on specific account or post, which the service provider would later look upon and decide removal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon decision, no mandatory reason would be presented to user whether the post were removed or not. Some criticized the reporting system as a potential way for social media companies to bring down contents in an unrestricted manner, e.g. social activists’ Facebook account closed without precaution, but the problem relies far beyond censorship on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The unknown redline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental flaw of an reporting system is the opaqueness of violation standard. While the majority of problematic contents removed were obvious enough, like spam or bot-generated content, the platform could not exempt themselves from controversial “edge case.” How much violence should a post be classified as “violent threat?” Social media websites tried to play a neutral role on speech regulation, but turned out trapped in a position no better than a court under autocratic regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even criteria that seems clear e.g. pornography face serious challenges. Free-the-Nipple movement participants got their account locked down by posting photographs containing nudity, while male with nipples exposed were perfectly fine&lt;sup id="fnref-7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The award-winning picture of Phan Thi Kim Phuc, known as the Napalm girl during Vietnamese War, were removed by Facebook also because of nudity&lt;sup id="fnref-8"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-8"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and later restored in sequence of an global outcry&lt;sup id="fnref-9"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-9"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Two significant cases demonstrates the hard-to-determine redline, which social media companies struggled their way — on which even U.S. Supreme Court haven’t succeeded further than “I know it when I see it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Privacy as its price&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further pose responsibility on users, an alternate approach to content regulation is to require users to provide their own identity. Chinese social media websites have been demanding real name for a long period, while Facebook recently asked part of its users to upload their identity proof. This could fundamentally harm the freedom of speech, as individual risks potential prosecution on expression in a police state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Regulations takes place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the 2016 U.S. presidential election, scholars have pointed out the potential danger on content filtering. We value both the authenticity of facts and the freedom of expression, while traditional court system model does not apply on the scale of social media. Under these prerequisites, we may propose the following possible regulations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, on the problem of content filtering, an individual’s right “to be untampered” should be established on social network services. Consider a  citizen born and lived in a digital era, an environment with diverse ideas is crucial, and companies should not be earning profit by exploiting the general public. One should be able to either turn off suggestions completely, or provided with options to switch to a side-by-side view of opinions contrary on social spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To deal with abuse procedure opaqueness, regulations need to be made to enforce social media companies present with their own transparency report. They should clearly state their standard on removal, number of removed posts, and of which percentage demanded by local governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in edge cases where the companies’ decisions were controversial, end users should be allowed to seek local courts to resolve the dispute, similar to an appeal procedure. The judicial system has far more familiarity with the restriction of speech and its possible consequence — we should not leave users stranded due to a lack of neutral third-party, but actively involved to protect their right to expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New media could same promote the idea of “marketplace of ideas”, just in a different way than traditional media. We have seen paradigm shift occurred once when newspapers adopt the idea of readers’ critique, where contrary ideas have their chance to make presence and enable choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Toward the era of Internet society&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of content filtering itself is the outcome of our own tendency on likes and dislikes. In an ever-evolving world with flattened hierarchy and borderless information access, lawmakers should get creative when facing Internet medium. Civil techies have already implemented fact checkers&lt;sup id="fnref-10"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-10"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; such as News Helper from the g0v community, and only more yet to come. How we encourage the common good of netizens, returning the power of Leviathan back to the mass public, would play a significant role on debate in the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook. (2016, September 30). Company Info [Newsroom stat]. Retrieved from &lt;a href="http://newsroom.fb.com/company-info/"&gt;http://newsroom.fb.com/company-info/&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin Weil (2010, February 22). Measuring Tweets [Blog post]. Retrieved from &lt;a href="https://blog.twitter.com/2010/measuring-tweets"&gt;https://blog.twitter.com/2010/measuring-tweets&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike Wendling (2015, June 29). What should social networks do about hate speech? &lt;i&gt;BBC Trending&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/blogs-trending-33288367"&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/blogs-trending-33288367&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben-David &amp;amp; Matamoros-Fernandez (2016). Hate Speech and Covert Discrimination on Social Media: Monitoring the Facebook Pages of Extreme-Right Political Parties in Spain. &lt;i&gt;International Journal of Communication&lt;/i&gt;, 10, 1167–1193.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「言論自由市場」，司法院大法官解釋釋字 414 號孫森焱大法官不同意見書、釋字 509 號吳庚大法官協同意見書參照。&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter. How to report specific types of violations [Help center answer]. Retrieved from &lt;a href="https://support.twitter.com/articles/15789#specific-violations"&gt;https://support.twitter.com/articles/15789#specific-violations&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amar Toor (2016, October 12). Facebook still has a nipple problem. &lt;i&gt;The Verge&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/10/12/13241486/facebook-censorship-breast-cancer-nipple-mammogram"&gt;http://www.theverge.com/2016/10/12/13241486/facebook-censorship-breast-cancer-nipple-mammogram&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-7" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julia Carrie Wong (2016, September 8). Mark Zuckerberg accused of abusing power after Facebook deletes 'napalm girl' post. &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/sep/08/facebook-mark-zuckerberg-napalm-girl-photo-vietnam-war"&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/sep/08/facebook-mark-zuckerberg-napalm-girl-photo-vietnam-war&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-8" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam Levin, J.C. Wong, &amp;amp; L. Harding (2016, September 9). Facebook backs down from 'napalm girl' censorship and reinstates photo. &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/sep/09/facebook-reinstates-napalm-girl-photo"&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/sep/09/facebook-reinstates-napalm-girl-photo&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-9" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;g0v News Helper [Home page]. Retrieved from &lt;a href="https://newshelper.g0v.tw/"&gt;https://newshelper.g0v.tw/&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-10" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>短文：道德的界線</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/2016/11/30/essay-the-moral-limit/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-30T15:46:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-11-30T15:46:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Poren Chiang</name></author><id>tag:blog.poren.tw,2016-11-30:/2016/11/30/essay-the-moral-limit/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「請以實際運動為例，提出理由來說明哪些（或哪類）增強選手表現的方法合乎道德，哪些則不合乎道德。）」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;一、問題意識&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在探討增強選手表現方法前，我們先將運動區分為兩類：一種是以選手個人身體的爆發力、耐力、延展力做為評斷標準，以展現物理上「身體素質」為目的的競賽，像是傳統的短跑、跳高、擲鉛球，都屬於此領域競賽的範疇（我們姑且命名為「體能競賽」）；而另一種則是以創新變化、策略分配作為致勝關鍵，以展現「表演技巧」、「團隊合作」為目的的競賽，像是溜冰、體操、水上芭蕾，除了體能訓練外，選擇的動作、表現的招式與團隊合作都需要額外的巧思（我們且稱之為「技巧競賽」。）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;而增強選手表現的方法，我們也可以根據個人付出的比率區分為兩類：一種是直接提升體能數值表現、無須運動員特別作為的道具，例如注射腎上腺素、睪固酮、或是提升紅血球攜氧效能的低壓氣密艙，我們可以以「力量藥劑」代稱這種科技；另一種是提升選手付出與訓練成果轉換率的方法，例如前往高山地區集訓、透過精密的睡眠與營養計劃調節體能狀態、或是應用負重或彈性束帶增強肌力，我們可以以 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「請以實際運動為例，提出理由來說明哪些（或哪類）增強選手表現的方法合乎道德，哪些則不合乎道德。）」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;一、問題意識&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在探討增強選手表現方法前，我們先將運動區分為兩類：一種是以選手個人身體的爆發力、耐力、延展力做為評斷標準，以展現物理上「身體素質」為目的的競賽，像是傳統的短跑、跳高、擲鉛球，都屬於此領域競賽的範疇（我們姑且命名為「體能競賽」）；而另一種則是以創新變化、策略分配作為致勝關鍵，以展現「表演技巧」、「團隊合作」為目的的競賽，像是溜冰、體操、水上芭蕾，除了體能訓練外，選擇的動作、表現的招式與團隊合作都需要額外的巧思（我們且稱之為「技巧競賽」。）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;而增強選手表現的方法，我們也可以根據個人付出的比率區分為兩類：一種是直接提升體能數值表現、無須運動員特別作為的道具，例如注射腎上腺素、睪固酮、或是提升紅血球攜氧效能的低壓氣密艙，我們可以以「力量藥劑」代稱這種科技；另一種是提升選手付出與訓練成果轉換率的方法，例如前往高山地區集訓、透過精密的睡眠與營養計劃調節體能狀態、或是應用負重或彈性束帶增強肌力，我們可以以「經驗增幅」形容這種訓練方式。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;那麼，我們便得以討論，對於體能競賽、技巧競賽兩種競賽形式，上述增強選手表現的方法是否合乎道德原則？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;二、原則檢驗&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;既然我們先以「運動的目的」區分出了兩種競賽形式，那麼自然以亞里斯多德的目的論作為切入點最為容易：亞里斯多德對行為的道德價值評價，取決於該行為是否能妥善執行所涉事物的目的，發揚事物的「德行」(virtue)；作為道德評價者，我們應秉持自己的理性、探求事物真實的目的，朝向美善生活而致力行動。在此基準上，只要增強選手表現的行為不違反該運動的目的，我們就難以認為其在道德上是錯的——例如以獨門的投球方式、混淆對手的戰略手法取得勝利，在技巧競賽的領域上就是可以接受、甚至是鼓勵的。為了發揚團體最佳戰力而採取有效率的訓練方式亦同。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;然而在體能競賽上，亞里斯多德理論的弱點也就暴露無遺：雖然經驗增幅的訓練方式與運動本身的目的並不相違背，但在力量藥劑的使用上，端視我們在「體能表現最極限、最精彩的競賽」之外對「體能表現是否透過真實訓練掙取而來」有無期待，會得到截然不同的答案——「可以，這將能讓選手有更亮點的成績、競爭更精彩」與「不行，這樣會使得賽事像是極限運動表演，違背了腳踏實地的運動精神。」一次次檢驗迫使我們不斷的補充、修正原本推論出的目的，但只以「有德者將做出有德的判斷」為最終判準，仍然難以作為普世的行為指引。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;那如果以康德的義務論作為判斷標準，有沒有辦法解決這個問題呢？首先，康德認為道德價值取決於動機，而行為的動機如果只是純粹發自個人的欲望、喜好、或是利益，屬於喜好動機 (motive of inclination) 的範疇，那便不具有道德上的價值。發自個人對自己訂下的道德準則，而且這準則是沒有前提、不帶條件的定言令式 (categorical imperative) ，我們才有可能透過評斷準則的好壞去評斷行為本身。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;康德賦予我們兩種工具進行分析：普遍法則形式，亦即「眾人是否能接受此規則成為普世價值？」以及目的自身形式，即「是否將自己或他者當作遂行目的的手段，忽視了自己或他人的尊嚴價值？」在實際應用上，我們可以說「運動員平時應該訓練」是一可普遍化的價值，而經驗增幅的增強方式可以被解釋為「運動員可以採取比較有效率的方式訓練」而被接受；採取有效率的方式訓練，也無損於其作為運動員的價值，因而可通過目的自身形式的檢驗。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;套用到亞里斯多德的困難案例上，我們難斷言使用力量藥劑、亦即「運動員應使用提升體能表現的藥物」是所有理性人都採用的行為依據：選手可能考量賽局困境，如果眾人皆使用藥物、則不會造成任何優勢，反而對身體有潛在傷害。從目的自身形式而言，我們可以認為「為了競賽優勢，使用提升體能表現的藥物」只是把自己的身體作為追求成績的手段，最大化的利用自己、卻未考量自己作為人的尊嚴與價值，所以不論是在體能競賽或是技巧競賽上，都是道德上錯誤的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;綜上所述，我認為在體能競賽、技巧競賽上，經驗增幅型的增強方式都是道德上可被接受的，惟力量藥劑型的增強方式是道德上錯誤的。&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>On the Path of Judicial Transparency</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/2016/05/01/essay-on-the-path-of-judicial-transparency/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-01T01:49:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-05-01T01:49:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Poren Chiang</name></author><id>tag:blog.poren.tw,2016-05-01:/2016/05/01/essay-on-the-path-of-judicial-transparency/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Criminal Justice of Japan: Traditions and Reformations” Final Report&lt;sup id="fnref-1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General disbelief of the judiciary system is not unfamiliar to Taiwanese people. Gone through colonial period under Qin Dynasty and Imperial Japan, the judiciary system on this island had evolved rapidly — from patriarchal, inquisitorial Traditional Chinese ruling conducted by district magistrate, into a more modern court approach, overseen by Governor-General of Taiwan&lt;sup id="fnref-2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Chiang Kai-Shek administration established Order of Martial Law which, under the effect of &lt;i&gt;Martial Law Act&lt;/i&gt; (戒嚴法), granted martial courts discretionary rights on criminal procedure&lt;sup id="fnref-3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, exposing citizens to the threat of martial prosecution. In the era later called the White Terror, political interference further worsened the reputation of jury system. Even in nowadays, “The courts are run by the Kuomintang” is a common explanation toward unsatisfactory court verdicts, and “dinosaur judges” (恐龍法官) is what netizens would call judges names of. Where could we, as practicers of law, put our efforts, to build the trust and transparency of our jurisdiction system, demanded by public?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report would briefly cover the differences between Japan’s practice of criminal procedure law and Taiwan’s, taking eavesdropping for example.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Criminal Justice of Japan: Traditions and Reformations” Final Report&lt;sup id="fnref-1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General disbelief of the judiciary system is not unfamiliar to Taiwanese people. Gone through colonial period under Qin Dynasty and Imperial Japan, the judiciary system on this island had evolved rapidly — from patriarchal, inquisitorial Traditional Chinese ruling conducted by district magistrate, into a more modern court approach, overseen by Governor-General of Taiwan&lt;sup id="fnref-2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Chiang Kai-Shek administration established Order of Martial Law which, under the effect of &lt;i&gt;Martial Law Act&lt;/i&gt; (戒嚴法), granted martial courts discretionary rights on criminal procedure&lt;sup id="fnref-3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, exposing citizens to the threat of martial prosecution. In the era later called the White Terror, political interference further worsened the reputation of jury system. Even in nowadays, “The courts are run by the Kuomintang” is a common explanation toward unsatisfactory court verdicts, and “dinosaur judges” (恐龍法官) is what netizens would call judges names of. Where could we, as practicers of law, put our efforts, to build the trust and transparency of our jurisdiction system, demanded by public?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report would briefly cover the differences between Japan’s practice of criminal procedure law and Taiwan’s, taking eavesdropping for example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Eavesdropping in Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communication inspection&lt;sup id="fnref-4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, literally eavesdropping, discovers and collects evidence by wiretapping suspects of potential crimes. Originated in investigation agencies The technique was developed to defend against large-scale criminal organizations, especially on the track of drug dealers in Japan since 1980s. Due to its massive infringement of personal privacy, considerable debate has risen around the constitutional legitimacy of eavesdropping. Specified in &lt;i&gt;Wiretapping for Criminal Investigation Related Act&lt;/i&gt; (犯罪捜査のための通信傍受に関する法律), wiretapping must only be practiced when critical crimes, (mostly organized homicide, drug smuggling, or weaponry trading) suspected, and the discovery of truth would render difficult without. In order to deal with the ever increasing trend of stimulant abuse, the Legislative Council (法制審議会) of Ministry of Justice concluded the act legitimate, while expanding its appliance on fraud, intimidation, illegal confinement and other victim-specific crimes in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Communication Security and Surveillance Act&lt;/i&gt; (通訊保障及監察法), established in 1999 and heavily revised in 2007, regulates more than wiretapping, extending its coverage to “wired and wireless telecommunication equipment to send, store, transmit, or receive symbols, texts, images, sound or other types of information”, “mail and letters”, “speeches and conversations” (Subparagraph 1–3, Paragraph 1, Article 3), which basically includes almost all possible communication methods imposed by modern society. On the other side, the definition of surveillance also states “intercepting, wiretapping, sound recording, video recording, photographing, opening, checking, copying communications or other similar necessary methods”, neutralizing the preposed protection offered by generalized definition. The Act defines similar requirement and restrictions on wiretapping, demanding such action only be performed to “protect from unlawful intrusion, and to ensure national security and maintain social order.” Contrary to the Japan regulation, right relief is not included in the revised Act, rendering the suspect vulnerable to unlawful wiretapping. Regulations on transcription creation also lacks in the current statute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall speaking, the legislative direction in Taiwan emphasizes “protection”, enlisting numerous principal statements on privacy; but since the actual practice of communication inspection (surveillance) often goes out of the boundary of written law, proper procedural protections after surveillance should be added in the future in order to realize aforementioned ideal and &lt;em&gt;due process&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Guilty Verdicts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Criminal investigation infringes the fundamental rights of people critically, thus should be carefully performed. Some called criminal procedure codes “constitution in practice,” thus its importance demonstrated. According to Ministry of Justice of Taiwan&lt;sup id="fnref-5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Japan&lt;sup id="fnref-6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the percentage of suspects being prosecuted in 2012 can be categorized as following&lt;sup id="fnref-7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Crime&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Taiwan (prosecuted %)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Japan (prosecuted %)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Homicide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;51.83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;34.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Robbery&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(70.46)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;53.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Causing Injury&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;32.02&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;40.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Larceny&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;56.05&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;42.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fraud&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;23.51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;55.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Intimidation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;33.44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;35.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Abrupt Taking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(70.46)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;18.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sexual Offense&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;51.83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;37.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Force Obscenity&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(63.48)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;45.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Public Obscenity&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(63.48)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;63.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Obscenity Distribution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(63.48)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;74.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dangerous Driving&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(54.55)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;88.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Public Threat / Setting Fire&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(54.55)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;45.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;House Invasion&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(30.75)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;43.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Currency Counterfeiting&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(30.21)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Forging Instruments&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;37.61&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;52.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gambling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;63.12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;46.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Weaponry&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;61.39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;36.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Drug / Stimulant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;55.12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;83.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Others&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(30.21)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;(N/A)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;41.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;35.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The five predominant crimes prosecuted in Taiwan were robbery, obscenity, gambling, weaponry, and domestic violence (not shown in the chart.) In comparison, the predominant crimes in Japan were death and injury caused by dangerous driving, stimulant abuse, bribery (not shown in the chart), obscenity distribution, and public obscenity. The two nations share a common pattern of higher prosecution rate on obscenity-related crime, which could be possibly caused by &lt;strong&gt;(i)&lt;/strong&gt; the simplicity of facts involved in cases, and &lt;strong&gt;(ii)&lt;/strong&gt; low social tolerance toward obscene materials or acts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is noteworthy that, though having stricter regulation, the prosecution rate of stimulant abuse in Japan could still maintain steadily at 81.2% to 82.3% from 2007 to 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the aforementioned report shows another interesting statistic number: convicted guilty in Taiwan stands roughly 95.7% to 96.6%, or roughly 1 out of 25 was declared not guilty; while Japan is constantly referred as 99.9%, which is about 1 out of 1000. How could we convince the citizens the investigation is reliable, if we couldn’t even enforce a reasonable procedure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve learnt about Citizen Judge System (Saiban-in system, 裁判員制度) on Professor Inoue’s intriguing lecture this semester, and how “lay judges” could stitch the gap between legal profession and citizens’ will. But, despite our Ministry of Justice eagerly seeks Advisory Judge System as the solution to judicial disbelief, the general public still treat “prosecution” as “guilty”, could we really bridge the gap only through “making citizens joining the case?” Properly restricting the authority could be the only, though difficult, path to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judicial reformation holds a long way ahead. By learning and comparing different regulation systems across nations, we believe a sturdy, trustworthy juridicial system could be more close to be established day by day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless noted, the reference listed on this report will follow the format of &lt;i&gt;National Taiwan University Law Journal&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;王泰升（2012），《台灣法律史概論》，臺北：元照。&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;〈戒嚴法〉第 8 條：「戒嚴時期接戰地域內，關於刑法上左列各罪，軍事機關得自行審判或交法院審判之。⋯⋯戒嚴時期警戒地域內，犯本條第一項第一、二、三、四、八、九等款及第二項之罪者，軍事機關得自行審判或交法院審判之。」&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;通訊監察 in Chinese or &lt;ruby&gt;通信傍受&lt;rp&gt;（&lt;/rp&gt;&lt;rt&gt;つうしんぼうじゅ&lt;/rt&gt;&lt;rp&gt;）&lt;/rp&gt;&lt;/ruby&gt; in Japanese.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;〈地方法院檢察署執行裁判確定情形〉，法務部網站，&lt;a href="http://www.rjsd.moj.gov.tw/rjsdweb/common/WebList3_Report.aspx?list_id=806"&gt;http://www.rjsd.moj.gov.tw/rjsdweb/common/WebList3_Report.aspx?list_id=806&lt;/a&gt;（最後瀏覽日：04/27/2016）&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;平成24年版犯罪白書（2012），日本國法務省網站，&lt;a href="http://hakusyo1.moj.go.jp"&gt;http://hakusyo1.moj.go.jp&lt;/a&gt;（最後瀏覽日：04/29/2016）&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numbers enclosed with parentheses indicates the data referred categorize data with lesser magnitude (e.g. “house invasion” is only shown under the category of “offense of freedom” from Taiwan’s Ministry of Justice.)&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-7" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>由「特殊性關係」思考不同語境下「性」的理解方式</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/2015/06/30/essay-special-or-sexual-hanzi-under-different-context/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-30T17:51:00+08:00</published><updated>2015-06-30T17:51:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Poren Chiang</name></author><id>tag:blog.poren.tw,2015-06-30:/2015/06/30/essay-special-or-sexual-hanzi-under-different-context/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2018/10: 這份是我大二到中文系選修「現代漢語語法」所寫的期末報告。因為選不到自然語言處理的緣故，賭氣決定去中文系越級打怪、認識看看文學院怎麼處理問題；雖然事先沒有語言學基礎、對當時的本系同學可能滿不好意思的，但也學到許多從來沒有想像過的分析方式。搭著當時新聞報導的熱度選擇「特殊性關係」這個題目，感謝一直很關心我的學習、十分溫暖的張麗麗老師。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;摘要&lt;/strong&gt;：這份報告將由討論「特殊性關係」一詞的岐異出發，分別探討「性」的不同詞義與使用情境，進而解釋「特殊性關係」的語法現象。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;關鍵詞&lt;/strong&gt;：漢語語法、語料研究、特殊性關係&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2018/10: 這份是我大二到中文系選修「現代漢語語法」所寫的期末報告。因為選不到自然語言處理的緣故，賭氣決定去中文系越級打怪、認識看看文學院怎麼處理問題；雖然事先沒有語言學基礎、對當時的本系同學可能滿不好意思的，但也學到許多從來沒有想像過的分析方式。搭著當時新聞報導的熱度選擇「特殊性關係」這個題目，感謝一直很關心我的學習、十分溫暖的張麗麗老師。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;摘要&lt;/strong&gt;：這份報告將由討論「特殊性關係」一詞的岐異出發，分別探討「性」的不同詞義與使用情境，進而解釋「特殊性關係」的語法現象。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;關鍵詞&lt;/strong&gt;：漢語語法、語料研究、特殊性關係&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;引言&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;選擇討論「性」這個詞作為研究主題，肇因於馮光遠（前中國時報副總編輯）在報章媒體上挖苦金溥聰（前國安會秘書長）一事。馮先生於文章中評論道，「金溥聰與馬英九之特殊性關係，政壇人盡皆知」，而被金溥聰先生一狀告到法院，雙方就該語句的語義內涵展開激烈論辯，成為系上眾人關注的有趣案件。
　　&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;問題意識&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自訴意旨略以：……被告意圖將系爭不實內容散布於眾，而藉由文字指摘或傳述系爭足以毀損自訴人名譽之不實內容於被告個人部落格，該等內容足使一般不特定之人誤認自訴人為同性戀者並藉由與馬英九總統間之特殊性關係而獲取職位，以致自訴人之名譽受到嚴重之詆毀，渠等即有誹謗罪之主觀犯意及客觀行為，而該當刑法第三一０條第二項之罪。另被告亦多次以公然之方式公然辱罵自訴人，其此種行為亦構成刑法第三０九條之公然侮辱罪。
&lt;div style="text-align: right"&gt;—— 臺灣高等法院 103 年度上易字 2515 號刑事判決&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;（被告辯稱）……對於附表編號 1、3、5、6、7 所敘及「特殊性關係」之解讀，其認為應解為「特殊性」關係，以別於「一般性」關係 ，亦即指當事人關係密切、交情匪淺等語。辯護人為被告辯護稱：由自訴人指訴及所提之證據資料可知，自訴人先入為主地將被告所述之「特殊性關係」一詞，全數解為特殊「性關係」，故被告所為全部評論，自訴人均指在影射自訴人為同志，並利用此等關係獲取好處，謂被告有加重誹謗等犯行云云，惟被告發表如附表所示之言論，主軸在強調「治國不可徇私」。至如附表編號 6 所示之言論，被告在自證 6 文章內提到馬英九總統將視為敵人之王金平院長，與視為自己人之自訴人採取不同處理標準，如此一來，將混亂國家體制及破壞司法公正等語，故被告強調以自訴人與馬總統間之「特殊性關係 」作為評論內容，非指自訴人為同志。
&lt;div style="text-align: right"&gt;—— 臺北地方法院 102 年自字 76 號刑事判決&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我們得以從判決書中窺出，對於名詞組「特殊性關係」解釋的岐異，是上開案例中最為核心的爭議。由此一爭點出發，我們因而提出疑問：「性」在不同語境下，該如何被理解與切分？藉由探討「性」的理解方法，我們希望能找到對「甲與乙的特殊性關係」在語言學上的解釋。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;文獻回顧&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;以語言學角度試圖解決法律問題，可追溯到哈特《法律的概念》對承認規則的肯認，以及法實證主義論者對法律語言中的模糊地帶，拋出之「無可決性」（indeterminacy）學說為始。他們主張語言具有「開放結構」，詞彙在「簡單案例」中或許能發揮它所指涉的核心效用，但在「困難案例」（或作「疑難案件」，hard case）中，圍繞在這些詞彙周圍的邊界意涵與延伸用法，便難以論斷是否屬於所稱詞語的範疇。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;《法律、語言與司法判決的確定性》一文則是指出，語言模糊只是背後有效社會共識缺乏的體現，對語義概念的理解，仍應回歸到語言所存繫社群的觀點而定。我們在分析「甲與乙的特殊性關係」這樣的詞句的時候，應由我們一般交際、表達的方式來分析它。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;語料分析&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;層次分析法&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;要分析「甲與乙的特殊性關係，人盡皆知」一句，我們首先考慮的當然是層次分析法。「甲與乙的特殊性關係／人盡皆知」是主謂關係，「甲與乙的／特殊性關係」是「定—中」偏正關係，「人盡皆知」為成語、不再切分。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在這裏，「特殊性關係」有兩種切分方法：一為「特殊性／關係」偏正結構，「特殊性」為「特殊＋性」所生的派生詞，其內部亦為偏正關係；一為「特殊／性關係」，性質亦為「定—中」偏正關係。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「特殊性／關係」的切分方式能在「特殊性待遇」、「材料的特殊性」、「太空科技具有其特殊性」等句法中重現，「性」在此作為衍生詞綴；「特殊／性關係」亦能於「伴侶間的性關係」、「發生性關係」等語句中使用，「性」在此作為詞組中的修飾語。兩者皆難以逕行認定為「罕用用法」，我們因而得以透過層次分析指出語法岐異的現象。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;詞義&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;為了進一步解釋這樣的現象，我們使用「中央研究院語言學研究所中文詞彙網路」搜尋了「性」在資料庫中的詞義：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;（ㄒㄧㄥˋ，xing&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;）&lt;br&gt;
普通名詞 Na  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;特定對象天生或長期養成的喜好或行為。（character）&lt;br&gt;
   例：仙人掌「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」好沙質弱鹼性土壤，如土壤粘重，可多施有機底肥，以增加通透性。&lt;br&gt;
   例：小黃瓜用來填飽肚子熱量又低幾乎沒脂肪，但是身體「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」寒的人應少吃瓜類，請酌量。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;個人的特有處事態度和心理特徵。（personality）&lt;br&gt;
   例：他身強力壯，心軟「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」直，不愛念書，就喜歡打架生事。&lt;br&gt;
   例：老人像小孩子一樣有自己的「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」，不能勉強，因此也要尊重他們自己的特質，「因材施教」。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;中醫依照食物特性所做的分類。&lt;br&gt;
   例：菠菜味甘「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」涼而質滑，有養血潤燥的功效；配以白米健脾益氣。&lt;br&gt;
   例：食物的溫、熱、寒、涼四「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」：魚鯰指生魚劊切製成，宜與蒜、薑、醋等同食，屬溫熱食物。羊肉「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」熱，同食易生熱。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;接尾詞。特定對象所具有的特性。（feature）&lt;br&gt;
   例：鏡片的透氧「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」是隱形眼鏡的重要指標，它的高低直接影響佩戴者佩戴鏡片時的舒適「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;為滿足性慾或生育等目的而產生的行為。（sex）&lt;br&gt;
   例：醫學界早已證實：除了「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」接觸外，血液。血液製品。醫療器械等途徑，都是不可忽視的愛滋病傳染媒介。&lt;br&gt;
   例：由醫科學生會在上學期末對一年級至六年級的醫科學生做的問卷結果中，七成的學生認為自己比一般人更認識「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;可以知道在「特殊性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;／關係」與「特殊／性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;關係」中的「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」與「性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;」並不屬於同個概括詞：「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」為「特定對象所具有的特性」之義，「性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;」則是「為滿足性慾或生育等目的而產生的行為」，雖然皆作定語，然而所指涉的對象完全不同。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;語料庫的分析&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;既然知道「性」在詞類上同屬普通名詞（Na），我們便可透過現代漢語平衡語料庫，試著由實境使用中找到規律。搜尋在語料庫中標記為普通名詞的「性」共有 824 筆結果，我們以統計學的亂數表抽樣方式，抽出 20 筆如下：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;600. ……晚上都能夠像新婚之夜真的是不簡單。其實我們說食色&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;也這是本性，可是食色性也，個人像飲食的需求也不……&lt;br&gt;
117. ……為加害人預留極大的脫罪空間。這種雙重標準就是「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;歧視」的一種後果或表現，它把「性」視為特殊的領域……&lt;br&gt;
591. ……應以六百字稿紙白話文書寫。題目包括：一、健全的&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;角色；二、我對性的認識；三、我喜歡我的性別；四、……&lt;br&gt;
190. ……者心態，對這個惡質情慾文化中的性騷擾、性強暴、&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;侵害、色情工業等等提出描寫與控訴時，性心情工作坊……&lt;br&gt;
10. ……想看又看不到。周：從字面上看這張畫，少男想在&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;上的第一次嘗試是比較年長的對象，如作者老師所說，……&lt;br&gt;
750. ……以發音為導向的輸入法，有其自然、可理解的被接受&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;。《註１．１．５》因中文字本身並不充分指示該字的……&lt;br&gt;
527. ……中很少見。女兒春所謂春宮畫即是描繪春宵宮幃男女&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;生活、各種性交姿勢的圖畫。通常裝裱成橫幅的手卷，……&lt;br&gt;
453. ……來惺惺相惜，如果我真的走到陽光下和我周遭的人談論&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;，別人又會怎麼看呢？」小方懷疑。以何春蕤為例，當……&lt;br&gt;
498. ……的上海大學社會系教授劉達臨指出，政治、經濟是影響&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;文化的主要根源。縱觀歷朝在「性事」方面的演變，有……&lt;br&gt;
736. ……有一些人，把性愛視作神聖的生命泉源。對於這些人，&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;與愛，就相當於生命與生活，絕對不能與娛樂遊戲……&lt;br&gt;
536. ……不過是文學中的一部分，不會特別熱門。由古至今，&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;觀念不斷在演化，人類不斷在尋求一個平衡點，現在……&lt;br&gt;
247. 重整&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;道德。自命是「消毒水」的現有性道德捍衛者，從不會……&lt;br&gt;
278. ……提出辯駁，他必須迎戰我對父權的各種情慾雙重標準和&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;壓抑所提出的嚴正批判，這樣才能深化我們對現有性……&lt;br&gt;
507. ……的關係、性技巧、姿勢、女性的性反應、受孕、禁忌、&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;功能障礙治療、草藥方…等等，可以說是一門中國古代……&lt;br&gt;
395. ……使用次數最多的前五版依次為測試專區、新聞交流站、&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;、您對本站的建議與鼓勵及聊天灌水五個版；交大……&lt;br&gt;
820. ……（每月將增加２萬筆），為國內外最大的中文書目索引&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;資料庫。另外，央圖更與全國２４所公私立大學院校……&lt;br&gt;
673. ……性是互相取悅，它的出發點是愛。有許多人可以把&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;和愛分開，我萬萬做不到。我是因為愛對方而渴望擁有……&lt;br&gt;
709. ……慘不忍睹，於是興起了重寫的念頭。我在書中所譴責的&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;泛濫，經過幾十年的潛伏期後，終於給人類帶來了……&lt;br&gt;
698. ……行事曆上，就像其他我不容錯過的約會或課程，而且將&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;看作生活中一件重要的事。雖然我們並不能隨心所欲，……&lt;br&gt;
699. ……我們已經從每星期做愛三次降到幾乎零次，因為我怕&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;會使我失去控制，而我曾極度地想控制自己，並且維持……  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;非常有趣的是，一反我們先前對「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」與「性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;」兩者常用程度不分軒輊的假設，針對語料庫的抽樣中，高達 85% 皆取「性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;」之意。在 95% 信心水準之下，抽樣誤差（兩個標準差）為 ±16%，亦即語料庫中非常可能至少有 69% 的「性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;」存在；而「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」與另外三種「性」的用法，只占語料庫不到 31% 的比例而已。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」的專有名詞色彩&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;上一節的結果令我們感到詫異：依詞彙被使用的比例來看，「特殊／性關係」似乎比「特殊性／關係」更容易為我們所理解！然而「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」為何相較於「性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;」較少被使用？對照抽樣自「中央研究院上古漢語標記語料庫」的資料：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;461. 《新語·道基第一》：水生陸行，根著葉長之屬，為寧其心而安其「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」，蓋天地相承，氣感相應而成者也。於是……&lt;br&gt;
584.《淮南·卷二俶真訓》：飛羽浮芥也，孰肯分分然以物為事也！水之「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」真清而土汨之，人性安靜而嗜欲亂之。夫人……&lt;br&gt;
161.《荀子·性惡篇第二十三》：人之性惡，其善者偽也。今人之「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」，生而有好利焉，順是，故爭奪生而辭讓亡……&lt;br&gt;
096.《莊子·在宥》：，不聞治天下也。在之也者，恐天下之淫其「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」也；宥之也者，恐天下之遷其德也。天下不……&lt;br&gt;
237.《呂氏春秋·孟春紀第一》：，必弗食。是故聖人之於聲色滋味也，利於「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」則取之，害於性則舍之，此全性之道也。世……&lt;br&gt;
180.《荀子·性惡篇第二十三》：之性惡明矣，其善者偽也。問者曰：「人之『&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;』惡，則禮義惡生？」應之曰：凡禮義者，是……&lt;br&gt;
390.《通玄真經（文子）·卷第十二上禮》：，性命飛揚，皆亂以營，貞信熳斕，人失其「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」，法與義相背，行與利相反，貧富之相傾，……&lt;br&gt;
532.《春秋繁露·實性第三十六》：禾雖出米，而禾未可謂米也；性雖出善，而「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」未可謂善也。米與善，人之繼天而成於外也……&lt;br&gt;
337.《通玄真經（文子）·卷第一道原》：，故莫敢與之爭。」老子曰：「夫人從欲失『&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;』，動未嘗正也，以治國則亂，以治身則穢。……&lt;br&gt;
638.《淮南·卷十一齊俗訓》：乘舟而惑者，不知東西，見斗極則寤矣。夫「&lt;strong&gt;性&lt;/strong&gt;」，亦人之斗極也。有以自見也，則不失物之……  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;可以見到，上古漢語中指涉「人與生俱來的天性」的「性」，反而占了壓倒性的比例，「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」作為衍生詞綴的用法，在上古漢語的語境中並沒有出現。然而如果將時間拉到清末民初的年代，黃克武先生於他的文章中這麼敘述當時的語言情況：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在 1895 年甲午戰敗後，嚴復開始從事翻譯工作之時，日譯名詞已經透過梁啓超（1873 - 1929）與其他大量留日學生的翻譯著作，以及日本人的漢文作品與報刊翻譯文字（如《時務報》的日籍譯者古城貞吉），大規模地進入中文。
&lt;div style="text-align: right"&gt;——〈新名詞之戰：清末嚴復譯語與和製漢語的競賽〉&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;對照日文中「経済性」、「可能性」、「アルカリ性」（鹼性）的用法，我們或許可以合理地認為，「～性」（「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」）是清末隨著西學東漸而引入的用法，帶有些略專有名詞的色彩。比較以下的語境：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. 這幅畫的象徵意義很特殊。&lt;br&gt;
B. 這幅畫的象徵意義具有特殊性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在日常生活中，B. 的使用多侷限於客觀、報導式的敘述手法，例如描述「這只手錶擁有非常良好的抗摔性、防水性、以及可延展性」，「罪行的構成要件該當、違法性、及有責性」，或是數學論證的「不失一般性（without loss of generality），設線段 AB 為相切於圓 O 且垂直於 x 軸的直線」。語料庫收錄文學與社會文章數大於科學與哲學作品，或許也說明了「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」於語料庫中占有較低比例的原因。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;結論&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在這篇報告中，我們先是得出了「特殊性／關係」與「特殊／性關係」兩種切分的可能性。而為了判斷何者為較佳的切分方式，我們抽離出了「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」與「性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;」兩種常見的詞義，得出了「性&lt;sub&gt;b&lt;/sub&gt;」較常出現於現有語料庫中，而「性&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;」客觀色彩較強、進而較少為日常對話所使用的結果。然而這是否代表「特殊／性關係」的切分方式就比較可取呢？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;陳坤先生於文中提醒我們，在司法案件中語言學的分析不可與語境抽離：面對當事人否認指涉對方性生活的主張，法官最終以文中曾出現「一般平民要如何期待政府部門保障文官制度的公平正義？……我們更應該堅守那條紅線，抗拒特殊性關係干預」等語，從嚴的認定馮先生僅是「尖酸刻薄的批評」而非影射「性關係」，最終採了「一般性關係」、「一般性貢獻」相對於「特殊性關係」、「特殊性貢獻」的說法。然而在一言一行皆會被記錄的現代社會中，語言學作為法院斷案的鋒利剃刀，說不定會越趨普遍呢。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;參考書目&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;臺北地方法院 102 年自字 76 號。&lt;br&gt;
臺灣高等法院 103 年度上易字 2515 號。&lt;br&gt;
陸儉明（2013）。《現代漢語語法研究教程》，4。北京：北京大學。&lt;br&gt;
王皇玉（2014）。《刑法分則講義》，國立臺灣大學法律學院（未出版），臺北。&lt;br&gt;
黃克武（2008），〈新名詞之戰：清末嚴復譯語與和製漢語的競賽〉，《中央研究院近代史研究所集刊》，62，頁 1 - 42。&lt;br&gt;
陳坤（2010），〈法律、語言與司法判決的確定性——語義學能給我們提供什麼？〉，《法制與社會發展》，16 卷 4 期，頁 61 - 72。&lt;br&gt;
吳東穎（2010），《論法律的無可決性》，國立臺北大學法律學系一般生組碩士論文。&lt;br&gt;
陳明通、陳盈瑜（2010）。《掌握問題意識，讓你看得明讀得通》。載於：&lt;a href="http://ctld.ntu.edu.tw/_epaper/news_detail.php?nid=95"&gt;http://ctld.ntu.edu.tw/_epaper/news_detail.php?nid=95&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>綻放的向日葵</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/2014/03/25/constitution-in-sunflower-movement/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-03-25T23:20:00+08:00</published><updated>2014-03-25T23:20:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Poren Chiang</name></author><id>tag:blog.poren.tw,2014-03-25:/2014/03/25/constitution-in-sunflower-movement/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;如果寫成超簡化的論證應該會被挑毛病，而且解釋憲法也不是算數學，不過我說個大概。過幾天會慢慢補齊前後文與論點。&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;如果寫成超簡化的論證應該會被挑毛病，而且解釋憲法也不是算數學，不過我說個大概。過幾天會慢慢補齊前後文與論點。&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(1) by 大法官釋憲329號，不論是條約或是協定「涉及國家重要事項或人民之權利義務且具有法律上效力者」，「除經法律授權或事先經立法院同意簽訂，或其內容與國內法律相同者外，亦應送立法院審議。」其中因為大法官不敢說台灣與中國是國與國關係，所以不解釋那塊，但可以確立重要性原則與法律保留原則是判斷需送立院審議與否的根據。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) 行政院之立論為兩岸人民關係條例第五條第二項「協議之內容涉及法律之修正或應以法律定之者，協議辦理機關應於協議簽署後三十日內報請行政院核轉立法院審議；其內容未涉及法律之修正或無須另以法律定之者，協議辦理機關應於協議簽署後三十日內報請行政院核定，並送立法院備查，其程序，必要時以機密方式處理。」之「無需另以法律定之者」，而逕行主張兩岸服務貿易協議為一行政命令，只需備查云云。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(3) 然而根據釋字第443號及 (1) 得知之法律保留原則，可以知道對人民權利義務有實質影響者必須以法律定之， (2) 之論點顯為錯誤。又，服務貿易協議涉及稅法之相關配套修正，並無所謂「未涉及法律之修正者」，因此 (2) 並不足採。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(4) 綜上所述，行政院之論述與前開憲法意旨不符，實屬違憲。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2014/12:   回顧大一的法律論述，覺得當時對法體系的理解實在很青澀呢。三一八對整個法律系、甚至是社會大眾全體，都是一次思想與價值的衝擊；在青島東路、議場、舊社科院禮堂度過的那些夜晚，對未曾深刻體會國家暴力的我們而言，更是褪去服從權威迷思，重新思考國家與人民角色定位的轉捩點。謹以後記自勉。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>圍城裡的春天：法律判決與文學</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/2013/12/29/essay-spring-in-a-chained-fortress-law-verdict-and-literature/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-29T17:01:00+08:00</published><updated>2013-12-29T17:01:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Poren Chiang</name></author><id>tag:blog.poren.tw,2013-12-29:/2013/12/29/essay-spring-in-a-chained-fortress-law-verdict-and-literature/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「請閱讀雲林地方法院91年度易字第258號刑事判決、台南高分院91年度上易字第985號刑事判決，比較二者的敘事風格，並另舉一裁判書為例，說明你認為裁判書應有的敘事風格。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一學期的法學緒論，敦促我寫了幾篇報告、思索過不少法律與社會的摩擦與競合，而學期末的最後一次作業，則是關於法律與文學表現的議題。課堂上受 RCA 毒害的阿姨、阿嬤，以及工殤協會為他們所做的口述歷史（《拒絕被遺忘的聲音》），則又是另一回故事了。&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「請閱讀雲林地方法院91年度易字第258號刑事判決、台南高分院91年度上易字第985號刑事判決，比較二者的敘事風格，並另舉一裁判書為例，說明你認為裁判書應有的敘事風格。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一學期的法學緒論，敦促我寫了幾篇報告、思索過不少法律與社會的摩擦與競合，而學期末的最後一次作業，則是關於法律與文學表現的議題。課堂上受 RCA 毒害的阿姨、阿嬤，以及工殤協會為他們所做的口述歷史（《拒絕被遺忘的聲音》），則又是另一回故事了。&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;劉登河是一位以撿拾廢五金維持生計的社會邊緣人。在民國 91 年間，他闖入了萬有紙廠的廢料堆置廠，將價值大約 100 元的廢鐵線搬上拾荒車，意圖變賣換取生活所貲。然而若要回收利用鐵絲，便先需將粘黏的大量塑膠屑燒燬融化、再剪斷搬運——登河先生正是在放火、毀損、竊盜等多項罪嫌的情況下由檢察官偵查起訴，並面臨累犯最低七個月、放火最高七年以下可能的有期徒刑。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;一、追跡法官的思緒&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;關於雲林地方法院判決&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;【91,易,258】&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「丙○○在法庭內等待叫喚的大部分時間，一直垂著頭，垂得很低，站起來說話時也沒有抬眼瞧著法官。他有嚴重口吃，說起話來，舌頭堵在上下齒緣，久久吐不出音來，臉部扭曲，深深的紋路，就更深了。一句話要說非常的久，而且說得非常的辛苦，法官又聽不太清楚。問他上學到那種程度，他表示唸到小學畢業⋯⋯」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在這份刑事判決書中，林輝煌法官運用大量的修辭與敘事，在制式的判決書框架中引入寫作手法，試圖將被告的情狀清楚地記錄於判決書中。不僅首開「抒情判決」之例&lt;sup id="fnref-liberty"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-liberty"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;，更引起司法人員的熱議與波瀾。承載著前科的背後，當事人的說法是什麼？「自從我被關了一年九個月回來後⋯⋯雖然我有口吃、找不到工作，但我還是意志很堅定，不再當小偷了，所以只好騎著三輪車到處撿廢鐵罐或紙類。」林法官細膩的整理了被告的背景、母親的供述、作出判決的歷程與考量，最後贊以：「法官願意相信，除非極度、極度的不得已，他會選擇有尊嚴的方式活下去⋯⋯上蒼悲憫，願容卑微生命在這塊土地喘息。檢察官慈愛，願為可憐小人物委屈。」判決罰金三百元，得易服勞役，以三百元折算一日。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;二、壁壘中的語言&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;關於臺灣高等法院臺南分院判決&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;【91,上易,985】&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;相較之下，臺灣高等法院臺南分院刑事第七庭所著的判決書，則較接近法院的標準用語，並以不少篇幅檢討原審之考量：「（原判決考量公訴人可能上訴，）本應為無罪之諭知而強為有罪判決，容有適用法則不當，而有入人於罪之虞；又⋯⋯以輕罪相繩，非但有違罪刑法定主義，尤非刑罰權之正當行使，且均有判決主文、事實與理由矛盾之違法。」並認為被告「恃媒體寵愛而驕縱，其母⋯⋯第一次開庭協同被告到庭時，即質問本院為何傳喚被告到庭，庭訊完畢復表示以後傳喚被告將不再到庭⋯⋯俱足見其藐視法庭。」判決書以原審、雙方之主張交互比對，並逐條或解釋、或駁斥，或許可視為邏輯縝密的法院文體。最後認為無法證明放火、毀損等罪，然而依然以刑法§321加重竊盜罪，處有期徒刑五個月，得易科罰金，並沒收鐵剪。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;三、城中綻放的花朵&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;前項判決之比較&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;人文關懷式的筆法，於判決中是否恰當？參考美國聯邦第六巡迴上訴法院的判決書&lt;sup id="fnref-usa"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-usa"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;，我們不難發現在這起運毒案中，法官以淺顯的語言敘述通案，縱然博引判例，仍不失其語言之平易。其以報導文學手法描寫全案之經歷，不僅清楚、甚至不必修習過英美法，也能了解法官的審案邏輯脈絡。在第一項所提及之雲林地院判決中，法官捨判決之標準語體，以簡單、柔軟的用詞，將無法為邏輯推演、量化的被告收錄於判決書中，讓未曾了解事件始末的我們，能以同理心度量、並贊同其認定；另一方面，高院臺南分院的判決書，文字清楚明確、論點縝密，著實建構了法院的權威、顯示司法邏輯清楚的一面。然而，這般「文言」的判決，真的能為民眾所接受嗎？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;結語：法院與網路時代&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;【98,北消簡,17】【99,訴,559】【101,簡上,115】&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;再舉戴爾電腦（DELL Computer）於民國 98 年 6 月間標錯價事件的判決書為例，法官於標準判決語體外，另外補述以：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「再者，本院忝為網路『鄉民』，於被告發生系爭標價錯誤事件斯時，亦親身參與其在 PTT、Mobile01 等 BBS 社群及網路論壇所引發之盛況，並親眼見諸多網友、鄉民於網路上藉此標價錯誤瘋狂下訂之『戰況回報』，本件被告固未能舉證原告訂購系爭商品，同係基於此藉被告之錯誤標價而貪小便宜、給大企業一點苦頭，甚至落井下石而得利之心態⋯⋯亦即，此時消費者即多有可能被認定係出自於『我也知道你不會履約，但是還是可以來賭一把，賭輸了也沒損失，賭贏了就賺到了』的心態，更使法院易為消費者對賣家之網路標價展示亦可知其僅為要約引誘之認定。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不難見到在判決書上藉由融入法官己身之背景與經驗，不僅能以更淺顯的方式說明原委，案件外的他人也容易透過口語化的譬喻，體會通案裁定理由之旨趣。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;最後再回到原先的問題，判決書應有的敘事風格是什麼？或許術語著實能夠堆砌法律的「圍城」，樹立司法的獨立、凌駕、慎重；然而在網際網路普及、政府資訊公開化的時代，法律人不僅需要與時俱進的認識社會，知識的普及更逐步重新定義了司法象徵的權威。或許簡單、清楚、淺顯、妥善使用敘事與文學手法的判決書，更能提升公眾對法院的肯定程度、影響人民對於法院的信任，甚至進一步的破除司法神秘的面紗。大法官們於釋憲已趨漸平易，作為人民與司法接觸的第一線，法院的判決又何嘗不能如此呢？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-liberty"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;蘇恩民（民 91 年 8 月 20 日）。&lt;a href="http://www.libertytimes.com.tw/2002/new/aug/20/today-c1.htm"&gt;〈抒情判決書 震撼司法界〉&lt;/a&gt;。自由時報。&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-liberty" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-usa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. 09-6497 &lt;em&gt;United States v. Skinner&lt;/em&gt;. Available at &lt;a href="http://www.ca6.uscourts.gov/opinions.pdf/12a0262p-06.pdf"&gt;http://www.ca6.uscourts.gov/opinions.pdf/12a0262p-06.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-usa" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>短文：號角背後的省思</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/2013/11/20/ntu-versus-concil-of-labor-affairs-explained/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-11-20T02:25:00+08:00</published><updated>2013-11-20T02:25:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Poren Chiang</name></author><id>tag:blog.poren.tw,2013-11-20:/2013/11/20/ntu-versus-concil-of-labor-affairs-explained/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;「臺大 vs. 勞委會」行政訴訟案，縱使了解來龍去脈的人不多，但相信不少人都看過&lt;a href="http://www.coolloud.org.tw/node/76232"&gt;臺大工會發雞排&lt;/a&gt;或是相關的&lt;a href="http://www.coolloud.org.tw/node/76217"&gt;新聞稿&lt;/a&gt;了。在宣判臺大敗訴的時候，大家都以為是臺大工會的重要勝利；然而在判決書出來之後，才發現行政法院其實還是滿冗的啊（汗。）受前輩的委託，寫了一份以一般人為預設讀者的判決重點整理；希望對試圖了解臺大工會的處境與挑戰的人，有所助益。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;附帶一提，&lt;a href="http://goo.gl/pkRlfz"&gt;申請&lt;/a&gt;加入&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/ntu.laborunion"&gt;臺大工會&lt;/a&gt;才能為《工會法》的團體協商保障噢。&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;「臺大 vs. 勞委會」行政訴訟案，縱使了解來龍去脈的人不多，但相信不少人都看過&lt;a href="http://www.coolloud.org.tw/node/76232"&gt;臺大工會發雞排&lt;/a&gt;或是相關的&lt;a href="http://www.coolloud.org.tw/node/76217"&gt;新聞稿&lt;/a&gt;了。在宣判臺大敗訴的時候，大家都以為是臺大工會的重要勝利；然而在判決書出來之後，才發現行政法院其實還是滿冗的啊（汗。）受前輩的委託，寫了一份以一般人為預設讀者的判決重點整理；希望對試圖了解臺大工會的處境與挑戰的人，有所助益。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;附帶一提，&lt;a href="http://goo.gl/pkRlfz"&gt;申請&lt;/a&gt;加入&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/ntu.laborunion"&gt;臺大工會&lt;/a&gt;才能為《工會法》的團體協商保障噢。&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;【102，訴，742】&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;臺北高等行政法院於11/7做出的判決，駁回了臺大對勞委會提起的行政訴訟，對臺大工會而言無非不小的勝利。然而此次的判決中，並沒有對「教學助理、兼任研究助理是否為雇傭關係」做出認定，也是各方將持續關注的議題。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;背景事實&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;教學助理（T.A.）、兼任研究助理（R.A.）、研究計畫臨時工，以下簡稱「助理」。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;101年1月20日&lt;/strong&gt;，「臺大工會」（工會 #1）向北市府申請成立。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;101年11月5日&lt;/strong&gt;，北市府認為「助理」不具勞工身份，扣掉這些人之後人數不足，不同意工會 #1 成立。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;工會 #1 向勞委會提出訴願。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;102年1月7日&lt;/strong&gt;，換了另一批申請人，向北市府申請成立「臺大工會」（工會 #2）&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;102年3月29日&lt;/strong&gt;，勞委會做成訴願裁定，認為「助理」具有勞工身份，撤銷北市府拒絕工會 #1 成立的行政處分。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;102年4月1日&lt;/strong&gt;，北市府核准臺大工會成立（工會 #2，也就是現行工會）&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;102年6月11日&lt;/strong&gt;，北市府通知工會 #1 的申請人，因為已經有工會成立了，無法再向北市府提出設立工會的申請，所以不同意工會 #1 成立。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;臺大不滿勞委會在訴願結果中認定「助理」具有勞工身份，提出行政訴訟。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;雙方陳述&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;這次訴訟中，臺大主張勞委會的訴願決定介入大學自治；承認「助理」的勞工身份，「將使大學無從教育學生榮譽感、責任心，」使得「師⽣倫常關係變質。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;勞委會則主張，訴願結果只是承認「助理」與臺大的勞雇關係，僅牽涉到工會能否成立；至於是否適用勞基法，是私法上的爭議，並不在行政訴訟處理的範圍內。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;法院見解&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;法院則是於判決書中指出，工會的成立的確關係到臺大的利益，但因為這次訴願牽涉到的，是當初提出申請、而被駁回的「工會」，與後來成立的臺大工會是兩回事；無論判決結果如何，都不能阻止已經有一個「臺大工會」成立的事實。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;至於教學助理、兼任研究助理及研究計畫臨時⼯（「助理」），無論是勞工身份的認定，或是公、私法的界定，法院認為並非雙方爭執所欲達成的目標（允許/阻止最早提出申請的那個「工會」的成立）；在這案件上再做爭執，也已經沒有實質的利益了，因此駁回臺大的告訴。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;文言版本：訴訟標的為工會之成立、而非司法雇傭關係之爭；工會既已成立，則已無訴訟實益。欠缺權利保護之必要，爰由法院駁回臺大之訴。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;結論&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;綜上所述，行政法院並沒有碰觸到 TA、RA 的相關認定，僅認為工會已經成立而判臺大敗訴。或許期待法院能挺身表明立場，尚言過早；但就另一方面而言，行政法院並未否定勞委會訴願決定的效力：工會在訴願大戰中搶占的灘頭堡，在此次行政訴訟中暫且穩住了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;至於臺大後續是否墨守規見、繼續採取法律行動？抑或願意正視學生的勞動權益、轉與工會協商？相信不只是臺大工會，各校、乃至於關心高教的各界人士，無不冀望臺大能率先作則、保障研究生的勞動權益，方不負國人對臺灣最高學府的要求與期待。&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>短文：抓住通姦的尾巴</title><link href="https://blog.poren.tw/2013/10/27/essay-what-is-adultery/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-10-27T23:37:00+08:00</published><updated>2013-10-27T23:37:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Poren Chiang</name></author><id>tag:blog.poren.tw,2013-10-27:/2013/10/27/essay-what-is-adultery/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;法律系的生活是忙碌且充實的。縱然大一少有時間放於課業，但課程中的詰辯、應答間對思想的衝擊，既新鮮又前所未有；著實足以令人卯起勁來，榨出八九個小時，完成一篇稚幼卻蓄積無數心力的報告。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;初次嘗試的題材就是通姦。或許是因為進度配合得剛好，或許是因為我對文字本就有執著，總覺得「解釋」是件十分有趣的差事。將法學院的生活命名為「桿秤人生」，某種程度上，也是由於對賴和手裏那把稱仔，有所掛心與感懷吧。&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;法律系的生活是忙碌且充實的。縱然大一少有時間放於課業，但課程中的詰辯、應答間對思想的衝擊，既新鮮又前所未有；著實足以令人卯起勁來，榨出八九個小時，完成一篇稚幼卻蓄積無數心力的報告。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;初次嘗試的題材就是通姦。或許是因為進度配合得剛好，或許是因為我對文字本就有執著，總覺得「解釋」是件十分有趣的差事。將法學院的生活命名為「桿秤人生」，某種程度上，也是由於對賴和手裏那把稱仔，有所掛心與感懷吧。&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;刑法第239條規定：「有配偶而與人通姦者，處一年以下有期徒刑。其相姦者亦同。」&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;請解釋以下兩個法律概念，並說明所運用的解釋方法：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;「通姦」  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;與「人」通姦之「人」&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;一、「通姦」之法律概念為何？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. 字義解釋&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「通姦」之法律概念，比起《刑法》其他規範，相對而言模糊得多。若以《教育部重編國語辭典修訂本》作參考，「通」作動詞解，為「男女間發生不正常的關係」；「姦」作名詞解，為「男女不正當的性關係。」而「通姦」一詞之確切定義，為「男女一方或雙方已有配偶而發生不正當的性行為。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. 比較法解釋&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在比較法解釋上，美國紐約州《刑法》第255條第17款第1項&lt;sup id="fnref-newyork"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-newyork"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;規範：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A person is guilty of adultery when he engages in sexual intercourse with another person at a time when he has a living spouse, or the other person has a living spouse.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;明確指出通姦（Adultery）為「當己方或對方有存活配偶時涉入性行為，犯通姦罪。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. 體系解釋&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;就體系解釋而言，我們能觀察到《民法》第1052條第1項第2款：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;夫妻之一方，有下列情形之一者，他方得向法院請求離婚：&lt;br&gt;
二、與配偶以外之人合意性交。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;並可以此推論，於現行之法體系中，刑法第17章〈妨害婚姻及家庭罪〉所欲規範之行為，應當與上開《民法》條文所列舉之「難以維持婚姻之重大事由」一致。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;又非合意之性行為，已有《刑法》第221條：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;對於男女以強暴、脅迫、恐嚇、催眠術或其他違反其意願之方法而為性交者，處三年以上十年以下有期徒刑。
前項之未遂犯罰之。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. 結論&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;前述之三種解釋方向，唯有字義解釋與其他兩者有所出入。然而考量辭典定義與法律概念可能有之出入，綜合以上所述、取其公約，可將通姦解釋為「有配偶之人，與他人發生合意之性行為。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;二、「通姦」的對象&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. 字義解釋&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;先就字義面解釋，「與人通姦」之「人」理應為上述所言犯通姦罪者之對價方；由前述導出之「通姦」意涵，意即除其配偶外，與有配偶之人合意性交者。又根據《刑法》第10條第5項：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;稱性交者，謂非基於正當目的所為之下列性侵入行為：&lt;br&gt;
一、以性器進入他人之性器、肛門或口腔，或使之接合之行為。&lt;br&gt;
二、以性器以外之其他身體部位或器物進入他人之性器、肛門，或使之接合之行為。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;可知性交於現行法規上，並不對性別加以拘束，&lt;strong&gt;看似&lt;/strong&gt;未於通姦對象有明確規範或限制。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. 歷史及體系解釋&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;然而就歷史解釋而言，根據立法院法律系統之立法紀錄，《刑法》第10條最早並無關於性交之相關定義。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;追溯《刑法》第10條第5項之制定，始為民國88年為配合第16章〈妨害性自主罪〉之修正而增列；而觀察該次修法於第16章第221條之修正理由第1、第2點：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一、原條文中「姦淫」一詞其意為男女私合，或男女不正當之性交行為，不無放蕩淫逸之意涵，對於被害人誠屬難堪，故予修正為「性交」。&lt;br&gt;
二、強制性交罪之被害人包括男性，故修改「婦女」為「男女」，以維男女平權之原則。  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;卻對「姦淫」設下了「男女私合」的定義。縱然民國88年之修法，並未對《刑法》第239條有任何變動；然而前述於字義解釋中，用以推論「通姦」之「性交」意義的法源基礎，卻是由一群認為「姦淫」是「男女私合」的立法委員所制定的。縱然我們可由修法理由第二點，看出修法者對男女平權原則之肯定；但僅依此推論「通姦之人」之實質意義並未對性別設限，尚有過度解釋之疑慮。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. 比較法解釋&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;根據《佛州法學評論》所述，將同性性交排除於通姦罪外的判例，倚仗於一條或多條以下所歸納之立論基礎&lt;sup id="fnref-florida"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-florida"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;需要兩名異性的性行為以構成法條規範之通姦罪；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;縱然法條並無要求行為本身始於異性，但所規範的、或法院解讀之性行為形式，僅可能發生於兩名異性之間；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;適用之法體系將通姦與肛交視作兩相異的違法行為；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;法規規範模糊，且法院依賴普通法對通姦的定義，而非援引教會法之立論基礎。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;若依此英美法體系之定義作檢驗，無論是前述紐約州《刑法》或是臺灣現行之《中華民國刑法》，無論同性婚姻合法與否，皆無將同性性交排除於通姦罪外之理由。縱然截至2011年為止，美國已有半數以上之州將通姦除罪化；然而在同性議題受高度關注的近代，尚保有通姦罪的各州法院對通姦之界定，無非具有一定程度的參考價值。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. 結論&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;「通姦之人」究竟能否囊括與通姦者同性之人？綜觀以上所論，縱然於歷史與體系解釋上，涵蓋同性「通姦之人」之立論基礎尚屬薄弱，然而就字義方面，法規並無對性別多作限制；就比較法解釋而言，亦可見規範用語之中性化，使得同性性交不被排除於「通姦」之定義以外。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因此，客觀上現行法規「通姦之人」應當同時包含同性、異性之合意性交行為。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;結語&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;通姦除罪化與否，國內社會爭議未平。然而在進行此次報告的推論過程中，不難發現我國對於性與婚姻之相關法規，仍缺乏一致且明確之定義；對同性、跨性等新興性別觀念，也未能跟進時代之腳步，於法規適用上予以清楚界定。過時的規範，難道就不可能因法官的主觀見解而侵害這些族群的權益？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;身為繼起之法律人，是否應以更積極的態度促成法規範的更新？所學尚淺，但暗許自己於學成之時，能夠成為成為倡導法律多元價值的生力軍。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-newyork"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N.Y. Penal Law § 255.17 Adultery.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-newyork" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-florida"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Nicolas, The Lavender Letter: Applying the Law of Adultery to Same Sex Couples and Same Sex Couples, 63 Fla. L. Rev. 97 (2011). Available at: http://scholarship.law.ufl.edu/flr/vol63/iss1/3&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-florida" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content></entry></feed>