<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 原創作品 | 任任的藍色虛空]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.poren.tw/categories/yuan-chuang-zuo-pin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.poren.tw/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-09T12:34:06+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.poren.tw/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Poren Chiang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[又一次的，白露]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.poren.tw/2011/09/13/another-whitedew/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-13T22:53:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.poren.tw/2011/09/13/another-whitedew</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>時光就在忙碌的一天天中悄悄溜走了。</p>

<p>灰濛濕漉的午後，穿梭著形貌各異的人群。水花啪噠啪噠的飛濺其中，喧囂的車潮瞬間掩蓋了我的輕跫。在車站外的街道上，一叢又一叢的行者交梭流湧，茫然的望向看不見的盡頭。雨後的台北陰沉的不像個亞熱帶都市，甚至帶了點秋季特有的一種悲涼。窗外的雨急切，如斷了線的思緒；玲瓏的濟城，草船般的借來座座箭林。托著腮幫子，我在教室裡靜觀一切的始終迭起，抗拒升上高二代來的忙碌時間壓力。</p>

<p>這是我第一次覺得歲月如此無情：玩笑般的提早赴約，又落下了最引人愁思的雨，牽起許多五味雜陳的回憶。</p>

<p>冬天是我行事效率最高的時節，最能讓我分神的卻是冬夜的一場大雨。黯無生氣的天色，呼嘯的朔風，緊閉的窗戶&hellip;&hellip;冬季帶來的，是被侷限的孤獨感，讓人覺得彷彿被困在城市的天際線下，再也踏不出一步。而雨的驟落，又更助長了這番冷冽挫人的氣勢。尤其向晚的綿延滂沱，是國三課業最繁重時，唯一伴隨我的單調風景。</p>

<p>而方過中秋，竟然就奇蹟似的降了全天的冬雨，若有似無的嘲諷了我與當時相仿的心境。高一情緒最低落的時刻，也是冷鋒過境前的連續霏霪。</p>

<p>日子就這樣過了，兀自迴旋於流逝的歲歲年年。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[百年孤寂]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.poren.tw/2011/02/23/a-hundred-years-of-solitude/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-23T23:23:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.poren.tw/2011/02/23/a-hundred-years-of-solitude</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2011，或說民國一百年，終於悄悄降臨。在新的年度裡，有許多盛大的活動籌備著，也有許多微小的希望等待發芽。然而，建國百年對我來說，似乎是一個價值觀重疊與衝突的年份。</p>

<p>歷史課本告訴我們，國民政府播遷來台，「民國」是由辛亥革命起算；迄今一百年的光陰裡，各式苦難摧殘著這個脆弱的國家，直至在台灣生根、發芽、茁壯。然而，自清朝割讓台灣以來的 116 年間，台灣已經在各國文化的先後影響下，發展出自己獨特的風格與社會。對於自大陸飄洋過海的一部份人民來說，台灣是最後一方自由的國家領土，認清現實的將大陸自法定領土中移除是不可以、也不能被容許的，因為那是他們對於故鄉與台灣最後一線的連結。然而對於土地上另一部分的人來說，唯獨台灣才為他們所認同；打著在國際上已於 1949 年滅亡的國家國號，是不切實際的。國家認同上的分歧促進了政黨間的對立，然而除卻政治的紛紛擾擾，有沒有人想過台灣這片土地本身呢？</p>

<p>古中國稱為蓬萊、東瀛的東側小島，在萬年的時間裡承載著豐富的動植物資源，被視為遙遠的海上仙山。然而短短的四百年間，這塊豐腴肥碩的土地先後的由<strong>荷蘭</strong>、<strong>西班牙</strong>、<strong>清朝</strong>、<strong>日本</strong>統治，遷移來的人民與執政者不斷的伐取資源，數以萬計的原生動植物被無情的轉換成經濟貨品出口販售。而日治時期直到今日的百年間，台灣更似一座孤島，在政治文化社經上，被各國無情的忽略。列強將它當作亞洲的一枚籌碼，中日將其視為貿易農產重鎮，美國也布局台灣為亞太軍戰要地。他們在談判桌上搶奪著一紙領土，卻未曾考慮過這個島本身要的是什麼？</p>

<p>建國百年，是政府引以為傲的一件事。然而台灣島百年來的興衰迭起與悲憤孤寂，會不會有如馬奎斯《百年孤寂》一般，在歷史上寫下曲折離奇卻又落寞的一頁呢？不知是悲是喜的這個年裡頭，我獨自憂心著這葉扁舟的未來。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[錦織秋夜]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.poren.tw/2010/09/21/weaving-the-fallnight/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-21T23:30:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.poren.tw/2010/09/21/weaving-the-fallnight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>暑假到雪梨、墨爾本一遊，認識了不少澳洲的新朋友。在 Facebook 上閒聊時，偶然談到中秋節，便換來一震驚奇：「Hang on&hellip;..you guys get a festival just to look at the moon? I&rsquo;m totally jealous.」於是花了點時間解釋中秋節的歷史背景。這些回應，被我整理潤飾後，貼在任任的藍色虛空國際版了。轉錄如下，各位可以花點時間看看。</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>Weaving the Fallnight</h4>

<p>Moon festival, or lunar festival, is a tradition in Chinese culture. Its distinctive point from other holidays, or a little disappointment to the government, is that the accurate date is calculated from moon phase. In the other words, cannot be fixed to a specific Gregorian date. We&rsquo;re unable to arrange it to Monday or Friday this year, which would make a continuous vacation.</p>

<p>So what IS the lunar festival? Actually, there are three lunar festivals throughout the Chinese history. The first one falls on lunar January 15th, which represents the end of Chinese New Year. On that day, people solves lantern riddles, cook sweet dumplings (with read bean soup usually), and prepare for another hard-working year. The Chinese name of sweet dumpling, &ldquo;Yuanshiao&rdquo;, is an alternative name to this festival.</p>

<p>The second one falls on lunar July 15th, which temples prepare foods for spirits and the dead. Activities for ghosts who still aren&rsquo;t reincarnated are held, and the lunar July is usually called &ldquo;Ghost Month&rdquo; since most good ceremonies (e.g. wedding, moving, etc.) have restrictions in this month.</p>

<p>And the last one is the so-called &ldquo;Mid-autumn&rdquo; lunar festival. Families usually get together in this day, having some tea snacks and enjoying the silver full moon. Since the round shape of moon symbolizes &ldquo;reunion&rdquo; and &ldquo;perfection&rdquo;, those who work out of the town often come back to country or wherever their family is. Moon cakes and boxes of sweets are given between friends and customers.</p>

<p>These festivals are established in Tang dynasty, and their real name literally is &ldquo;[Upper] Yuan Festival&rdquo;, where the upper, middle, lower parts of a year represents the sacrifice ceremony of sky emperor, earth emperor, and water emperor. They are intended to bring people good luck, and hope the gods, the dead, and the nature live in a balance. So regardless where you&rsquo;re living in, just prepare some tea and enjoy yourself with moon-gazing! :)</p>

<p>RenRen @ Blue Nowhere @ Taipei, with gorgeous shining moonlight.</p>

<p>祝福各位，中秋佳節快樂幸福。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
